A Guide to the Charles Ramsdell Papers, 1844-1942.
Charles Ramsdell Papers
1844-1942
Ramsdell, Charles W. (Charles William), 1877-1942.
23175416
14 ft., 1 in.
Dolph Briscoe Center for American History, The University of Texas at Austin
Papers concern the career of Ramsdell and include materials relating to his teaching responsibilities; documents concerning his activities with historical organizations; correspondence and other materials relating to his research and writing.
Biographical Note
Charles William Ramsdell, Sr. (1877-1942) was born at Salado, Bell County, Texas. His entire career was associated with the University of Texas (UT), which he entered as a student in 1900. He received B. A. and M. A. degrees from UT in 1903 and 1904, respectively, and a Ph. D from Columbia University in 1910. On August 26, 1906, he married Susan Griffith, and the couple had two children, Dr. Mary Alice R. Dye and Charles William Ramsdell, Jr. From 1906 until his death on July 3, 1942, Ramsdell taught for the history department at UT, although he held visiting lectureships in the state universities of Illinois and at Columbia, Northwestern, Western Reserve, and Duke Universities. Although classroom teaching was his primary interest, Ramsdell wrote widely. A bibliography of his publications includes three books, several edited works, numerous articles and monographs, as well as many contributions to reviews. His books include Reconstruction in Texas, A School History of Texas (in collaboration with Eugene C. Barker and C. S. Potts) and Behind the Lines in the Southwestern Confederacy (published posthumously).
The several historical associations in which Ramsdell was active recognized his eminency. He served as president of the Mississippi Valley Historical Association, 1928-1929, and of the Southwestern Historical Association, 1936. He was a member of the executive council of the American Historical Association from 1931 to 1934. The Texas State Historical Association elected him treasurer annually from 1907 until his death, and he was an associate editor of its Quarterly from 1910 to 1938.
Recognized as the dean of Southern historians, Dr. Ramsdell held the distinction of being the most distinguished scholar and teacher in the field of Southern history.
Scope and Contents Note
The Charles Ramsdell Papers, 1844-1942, concern the career of Ramsdell and include materials relating to his teaching responsibilities; documents concerning his activities with historical organizations; correspondence and other materials relating to his research and writing. Also included is an inventory of his library, which was donated to the University of Texas, and an 1844 letter concerning a Mississippi Whig's opposition to the annexation of Texas. The library also holds an extensive collection of microfilmed documents concerning Southern history, which were collected by Ramsdell. There is a separate index to the microfilm collection.
Access Restrictions
Use of photographic negatives requires an appointment; please contact the photos archivist for more information.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Ramsdell, Charles W. (Charles William), 1877-1942 -- Archives.; Ramsdell, Charles W. (Charles William), 1877-1942--Photographs.; Ramsden family--Photographs.
Subjects
Books.; Frontier and pioneer life.; History--Study and teaching
Places
Texas--Annexation to the United States.; Confederate States of America--History--Sources.
Detailed Description of the Papers
- Inventory
  - Students Papers, 1924 (Box 2F445)
  - Notes, 1924
  - Notes. (Box 2J186)
  - Grade books.
  - Literary Productions.
  - General Correspondence: (Box 2L461)
    - 1908-1912.
    - 1913-1914. (Box 2L462)
    - 1915-1918. (Box 2L463)
    - 1919-1920. (Box 2L464)
    - 1921-1922. (Box 2L465)
    - 1923-1926. (Box 2L466)
  - Relating to Southwestern Intercollegiate Material Relating to Teaching Responsibilities Material Relating to Historical Associations Correspondence Relating to Organizations of College History Teachers, 1922 (Box 2L467)
  - Financial Records, 1911-1925
    - Receipts, Check Stubs, 1911-1914.
    - Receipts, Cancelled checks, Bills, 1907-1925 and undated (Box 2L468)
    - Check Books, Deposit slips, Miscellany, 1911-1914.
  - Printed Material, 1910-1923 (Box 2L469)
    - Newspaper clippings, handbooks, 1910-1923.
  - Miscellany, 1922-1942.
  - Inventory of the Library of Dr. C. W. Ramsdell, 1942. (Box 2R157)
  - Copies of Letters Sent to C. W. Ramsdell.
  - Correspondence of C. W. Ramsdell, 1922-1941.
  - Correspondence: (Box 3N290)
    - A-M, 1932-1938.
    - N-Z, 1932-1938. (Box 3N292)
    - A-Z, 1937-1938.
    - A-Z, 1930-1936. (Box 3N293)
    - A-B, 1934-1935.
    - C-Z, 1934-1935. (Box 3N294)
    - A-Z, 1931-1934.
    - A-Z, 1931-1934. (Box 3N295)
    - A-Z, 1932-1935.
    - A-Z, 1926-1934. (Box 3N296)
    - A-C, 1928-1932.
    - D-Z, 1928-1932. (Box 3N297)
    - D-Z, [no order,] 1931-1932.
    - D-Z, [no order,] 1931-1932. (Box 3N298)
    - A-Z, 1933-1936.
    - A-P, 1916-1922.
    - R-Z, 1916-1922. (Box 3N299)
    - A-Z, 1922-1923.
    - A-Z, 1925-1926 (Box 3N300)
    - A-Z, 1924-1925.
    - A-Z, [no order,] 1928-1929 (Box 3N301)
    - A-Z, 1928-1940.
    - A-Z, 1930-1931.
    - A-Z, 1929-1932. (Box 3N302)
    - A-R, 1934-1937.
    - S-Z, 1934-1937. (Box 3N303)
    - A-Z, 1938-1939.
    - A-Z, May-November, 1939. (Box 3N304)
    - A-J, November 1939-May 1940.
    - K-Z, November 1939-May 1940. (Box 3N305)
    - A-Z, June-November 1940.
    - A-Z, January-October 1941. (Box 3N306)
    - A-C, November 1941-1942.
    - D-Z, November 1941-1942. (Box 3N307)
    - D-Z, 1941-1942, no order
    - Annexation Letter, 1844.
  - Notecards and Exam Questions for Courses Taught, 1941. (Box 3N308)
  - Notecards and Exam Questions for Courses Taught, 1941. (Box 3N309)
  - Notecards and Exam Questions for Courses Taught, 1941. (Box 3N310)
  - Photographs, undated. (Box 3S20)